we want to
write a program that prints a given
string repeatedly
until a certain number of lines has been
printed
and we're going to ask the user to
dictate the number of lines
greater than or equal to three the
problem gives us
a detailed example of how the program
should run
to help us along as we write this code
we know we want to prompt the user
[Music]
how many output lines do they want
and we're dictating that the number of
lines should be
at least three we want to store the user
input in a local variable
and we'll call that local variable
number of lines
give it a nice descriptive name
and we'll use get s to capture that user
input
now knowing that all user input comes in
as a string
and we need to use this input as an
integer
we'll go ahead and call 2i on that user
input when we store it in our local
variable
for now let's just run our code with the
prompt as is
and print the number of lines back out
to ourselves
so we'll enter five
[Music]
and the program prints that back to us
so we can see that our
number of lines was successfully stored
in the local variable
now what happens if we input a number
less than three
i'll input one
[Music]
at this point the program doesn't object
so we need to build that functionality
in
[Music]
we can achieve this by putting our
prompt into a loop
and we'll break out of the loop when we
get the desired input from the user
[Music]
so we know the condition of breaking out
of this loop should be
if the number of
lines is greater than or equal to three
let's run our code again
this time you'll see that if i input a
number less than three
i'll input one our loop continues to
iterate
and we're prompted again
[Music]
now i'll input 3 and see if our code
breaks out of the loop
[Music]
and it does
now we want to output some type of error
message to the user if the number they
enter
is less than three
so we can display
that's not enough lines
[Music]
running the code again you can see our
error message
and the prompt displayed again
[Music]
we want to output the string launch
school is the best
number of lines times so if the number
of lines is 3 we want to output the
string three times
and we want to do this after we verified
that the user has input a valid number
of lines
so after we break out of our loop
we want to print this line but we need
to control how many times it's printed
based on what the user input was we can
use the local variable
number of lines as somewhat of a counter
we can use a while loop
and say while number of lines is greater
than zero
[Music]
and decrement number of lines each time
that we
iterate through this loop and we'll do
that by reassigning number of lines
to number of lines minus one
now there's a problem in our code and
hopefully you've already spotted it
number of lines was initialized on line
three
in the inner scope of this block passed
to our loop method
so as our code is currently written we
can't actually
access number of lines and let's run our
code and see that
[Music]
i'll input 4 for how many lines we want
and you can see that on line eight
we have an undefined local variable or
method number of lines
so we're unable to access number of
lines outside of the inner scope of the
block in which it was initialized
and in order to solve that we'll simply
initialize number of lines
on line one
now when our program executes line one
we don't yet have a value to assign to
number of lines
since we need to wait for the user to
give their input
so we'll simply assign it to nil now
let's run our code
and see what we've got
[Music]
first i'll enter 2 which is going to be
an invalid number of lines
i see my error message and i'm prompted
again
this time i'll enter four
[Music]
and our string was printed four times